so you just finished some in-depth work on a 6502 CPU emulator
now you might think that the only reason we ever use CPU emulators
are for learning and they're great for learning right so i can give you
a screen and it has a program counter and a z flag and an n flag
and instruction memory and you can go change the instruction memory you can
start it you can stop it it prints a lot of stuff out you can
hover over an instruction and it shows you what the instruction is and what
the ASCII character might be stored there etc etc etc and it keeps it really
simple so we can write pretty small programs
we can also look at the emulator code itself and i've got in the upper corner
a url that is the actual machine code emulator that's running when you're
doing your assignments or just playing with it
so if you go look at that it's javascript and you've learned javascript
and it has to run in the browser so i have implemented
a 6502 instruction set in javascript in a browser the core of this is a
function called execute step which should be called like fetch execute
cycle because what it really does is it's going to run one instruction so
which instruction is it going to run well you can see in that first
line it's going to look at this.cpu.pc the program counter
where are the instructions well they're in an array so we're going to use the pc
to look up the instruction in the array what's the instruction
it's an integer from 0 through 255 it's a single 8-bit number
and so the next thing it's going to do is have a big long if then else with like
40 or 50 different instructions the first instruction it checks to see is if
we got all zeros well the 000 instruction is the break
the halt and so what happens is the the the emulator
prints the output from the from the data memory
and then it sets itself to not running and then the fetch execute cycle
stops and there's a bunch more else else else else is
if it doesn't find an instruction that it understands it has one last else
that blows up and sets it to running equals false
you might just go have some fun and see if you can figure out a bit pattern
that will cause the emulator to blow up with an unknown instruction
and after we processed one instruction well we advance the program counter it's
what we do with the fetch execute cycle now if there was a jump if one of those
instructions was jump instruction it already changed the pc do remember
how i told you that a jump instruction is kind of like a
load into the pc it's almost like a load immediate into the pc
so that that code up in the instruction processing sets the pc increment to zero
to indicate that it's already been changed to a completely new location
by a jump so if the pc increment is greater than zero we simply say
add the pc increment that little mask is there
to make sure it doesn't get bigger than 256 because there's only 256
instructions in the instruction memory and the pc increment
is going to either be one if it's an 8-bit instruction
or two if it's a 16-bit instruction digging a little more deeply into some
of those else if else if else if else if you can
see the load accumulator immediate instruction
it's a 0x89 and what we do is we say oh let's get that
immediate value take that cpu instructions and go one
beyond the pc and grab it so that's the number that
we're loading and what do we do well we take the
immediate value and put it in the accumulator
and every time you change the accumulator you got to update the z in
the end flag so we got a function to do that
and then we say hey this was a 16-bit instruction increment the pc by two
subtract immediate again we grab the immediate which is the immediately
following after the program counter we compute the difference and then we
set the accumulator to be the difference update the status flex because we
change the accumulator and set the pc incremented to we do like
something a little more complex which is a
load with an address and an offset by the x register
again the base address is an immediate so we go one beyond the
the program counter and grab that then we grab the x register
make sure it's a number not a string that that's that's probably just
conservative programming then we take the base address plus the
x value that's our offsetting to our our index by x
and then we go grab the real memory cpu dot memory of the effective address
what is memory here's a 256 byte array and then we set the accumulator to
whatever came out of that memory and we update the status flags
and we set the p increment to two so again this is about 1300 lines of code
i would not claim it's a perfect emulator i just did it
well enough to make it so that you can learn what you need to learn in this
class i would say probably i could make it
a lot more accurate if i made it 2500 lines of code
if i did things like made all the memory mapping for sound and stuff work it
probably be three or four times larger maybe five
thousand lines of code that's not a lot of code the interesting
thing is that most modern processors on phones and computers
are so fast that even if we're writing something in javascript
that's emulating historical machine code it can do that
far faster than the original hardware so if you build an emulator for a 6502
and you want to do one megahertz well you probably will have to slow it down
and things like graphics are way better in modern environments and they
they don't take a lot of resources so if we go back
to the 70s and the 80s people would buy things like
atari 2600s and play them on their televisions
they would have these these plug-in rom modules that had the code in it that's
the machine code and so there's an effort to capture these
and you can actually disassemble these their roms are
things you can read with rom readers and then you can extract the machine
code and then you can build an emulator and it turns out that the
atari 2600 is a has a 6502 in it so the
console that you plugged into the atari 2600
that machine code is 6502 machine code so you build an emulator
including all the graphics capabilities of the 2600
and so you can emulate a game like space invaders
on the atari 2600 in your browsers and completely play it i encourage you
to go ahead and play it if you slow down the
startup now once things get cached in your browsers this screen goes by so
fast you won't even see it i had to record it to catch it
you can see what's going on as the game is being loaded
it's looking at the files it's the the machine code for the game and it's
running it in the browser using a piece of software
written in wasm now it's not written in javascript it's written in wasm what is
wasm wasm is web assembly so i built a machine language emulator
in javascript that you are using but there is a low level high
performance machine language emulator built into web browsers
recent web browsers called web assembly so web assembly is a machine code that
is not intended to be built in hardware but intended to be
emulated very very rapidly by hardware so for a wide range of software you can
do surprisingly complex things and then compile them to wasm download
them into a browser and run them in a browser with a little
javascript library that provides things like file opening etc etc
now i want to show you a bit of wasm it's got a little bit different syntax
than most assembly languages but it still is a very succinct one-to-one
correspondence to binary machine code i will also show you in the c programming
for everybody course that i teach at www.ccfree.com
the c playground actually doesn't run the code in the server it compiles c to
wasm in the server and then runs wasm in the user's
browser so you can't run an infinite loop in my c
programming for everybody course and break my server you can write an
infinite loop and break your browser but that is your browser so let's take a
little bit of a look at web assembly wasm is a little bit different so you
don't see for example an accumulator it actually has a stack and it has
operands on the stack and it you put operands on the stack
and then you operate on the operands of the stack and they replace things on the
stack it's a very simple execution model but
it's still very very low level and what this is is this is printing
hello world you see this sort of indentation it it still is machine code
if you look below there's about 90 bytes of machine code
that i dumped from this particular bit of code compiled into wasm
it uses a little different syntax because it really doesn't want to
expose labels in wasm it really wants there to be a stack
it wants to be a set of nested like modules and variable scopes and things
like that but still it's an assembly language and
it is got nesting so so you tend not to use labels in the same way
that we use labels in more traditional assembly language
and machine language and here is a simple example of a
thing you can just go to this website and play with it you can
write c code you hit the run code button it uploads the c code to a server which
then compiles it to wasm that takes very little time and it
downloads that wasm and then it runs that wasm as output and
shows the output of it that also means that in that wasm
compiler for c there's a whole standard library
includes sddio.h and the printf that's been compiled to wasm as well
so the wasm you get back from in scriptum is much larger
than a just a pure wasm bit of code because it's compiled
the c library as well so that you can do things like printf and scanf and
other kinds of things that you would do in a
c application so emulators going forward are so fast
and becoming ubiquitous that it's kind of foolish to write
native code for certain things like video games and
and other things and so the the fact that you're playing with an emulator
going forward in the future you may be writing code for production
that runs in an emulator